Guide to the James Silverberg Papers 1941-1994
University of Chicago Library
Silverberg, James. Papers
1941-1994
27 boxes (14.5 linear feet)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
James Silverberg, Professor of Anthropology department at the University of Wisconsin - Milwaukee. As a graduate student he accompanied Gitel P. Steed on the Columbia University Research in Contemporary India Field Project. The bulk of the papers are related to the India Field Project. Additionally, there are files regarding the creation and organization of the Steed archive. There is also a small collection of Silverberg's writings and correspondence.
Information on Use
Access
Series VI contains financial material that is restricted until 2039.
Biographical Note
There are few biographical materials housed in the James Silverberg Papers. He worked with Gitel P. Steed as a graduate student, traveling with her to Gujarat, India, as part of the Columbia University Research in Contemporary India Field Project. He was accompanied by his wife, Donna. Silverberg later taught at the University of Wisconsin - Milwaukee. He died in 2001.
Scope Note
The James Silverberg Papers contain 14.5 linear feet of material and roughly cover 1941-1994, though the bulk of the materials were generated between the late 1940s and late 1970s. The collection consists largely of Silverberg's research materials, which include: field notebooks, quantitative data, surveys, maps, reports, interview transcriptions, etc. These materials relate exclusively to his work in India, though they do cover several different research trips. Much of the qualitative data should prove useful and interesting to researchers interested in 20th century India and, especially, the Indian caste system.
In addition, the Papers house a small collection of writings and correspondence. The former contains typescript and reprint copies of Silverberg's work, both published (articles) and unpublished (talks, conference papers), as well as related correspondence. The latter contains a mix of personal and professional correspondence. The James Silverberg Papers also include a series of general files in which materials unrelated to the established taxonomy of the collection can be found.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Gitel Steed. Papers
Subject Headings
Silverberg, James; Steed, Gitel Poznanski; Caste -- India; Gujarat (India) -- Social life and customs; India -- Economic conditions -- 1947-; India -- Religion; India -- Social life and customs
INVENTORY
- Series I: Writings
  - Subseries 1: Dissertation, "Peasant Behavior and Its Caste Relevancy: the Kolis of Kassandra"
    - Correspondence, notes, partial draft typescript, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Partial copy, notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Complete copy, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Chapter one, "General Setting: The Land, the Village Community, and the Koli Castes," typescript, notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - "Multiplicity and Cross Caste Duplication of Koli Economic Roles - First Draft (Second Copy)," typescript, notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Kolis as Service Recipients," typescript with commentary, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Koli Production Roles," typescript, notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Koli Proprietary Roles," typescript, notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Typescript titled "Koli Social Roles," undated (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    - Typescript titled "Kolipatel Political Roles," notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - "Probably Chapter 4 or 5: Political Roles," typescript, notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries 2: General Files
    - "Background Chapter - First Part (1953)," typescript, notes, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Diverse Field Techniques in India," meeting of CSAS, Urbana, IL, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Caste in the Village," University of Wisconsin - Madison, notes, correspondence, syllabi, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Caste-Ascribed ‘Status’ versus Caste-Irrelevant Roles," Man in India, publication, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Eye-witnessing Modes of Production in Indian Villages in Order to Introduce a Solar Energy Technology," 10th International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, typescript, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Lecture re development and the role of personality in an historical-functional context, delivered to Barrett’s culture-personality class, notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Notes for talk delivered to the Asia Club, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Introductory Statement," typescript, notes undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified typescripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Notecards for unidentified work, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1953-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence regarding research in India, 1949-1952, SEE ALSO Series III: Research (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence regarding Gitel Steed papers and the preparation of a Steed biography, 1986-1987, Correspondents include: James Silverberg, McKim Marriott, Robert Steed, and Riva Berleant-Schiller SEE ALSO Series I: General Files, Subseries II: Materials Related to Gitel P. Steed (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Marriott, McKim, correspondence regarding Steed-Columbia India Field Project Archive and Silverberg’s appointment to the University of Chicago’s Committee on South Asian Studies, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Silverberg, Donna, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Steed, Gitel P., 1952-1971, SEE ALSO Series I: General Files, Subseries II: Materials Related to Gitel P. Steed (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Steed, Robert, 1971-1985, SEE ALSO Series I: General Files, Subseries II: Materials Related to Gitel P. Steed (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, Correspondence regarding Silverberg’s application for a sabbatical year and retirement, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series III: Research Materials
  This series contains materials related to Silverberg's research in India. The bulk of these materials were generated as part of the India Field Research Project, headed by Gitel P. Steed. They have been separated according to geographic region and theme: Bakrana, Kasandra, caste system, and unknown or general India. The first two Subseries are named for villages located in the state of Gujarat. Subseries III deals specifically with the caste system, a major theme in Silverberg's research. Finally, the materials whose geographical provenance is unknown or which relate to India generally have been housed together in Subseries IV, though it is probable that they were generated in either Bakrana or Kasandra. Researchers are advised to examine the materials in Subseries IV should they be interested in Subseries I, II or III.
  - Subseries 1: Field Research Materials - Bakrana (Gujarati Village)
    - Transcripts of interviews conducted in Bakrana, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    - Field notes, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Field notes, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 1-11)
    - Field notes, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
    - "India Gujarat Bakrana," computer disks, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Informant List, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Notes on the Bakrana Census Code Book, general census notes, 1950, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Bakrana, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - to archive on Bakrana, undated (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - Description of curing ceremony, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Notes housed in folder titled "Steed’s "Classified Index,"’ undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Genealogical map, notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Field Research Materials - Kasandra (Gujarati Village)
    - Notes on Kasandra, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Notes on caste subdivisions, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Notes on in visiting, out visiting, the ritual cycle, and the agricultural cycle, 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 9-13)
    - Notes and partial typescripts on social rules and behavior, correspondence, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Maps, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 3: Field Research Materials - Koli Status and Caste System
    - Questionnaires on Koli status in various areas of Gujarat, commentary on these questionnaires, related correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 9, Folder 16-19)
    - Field notes on caste system in Gujarat, collected in multiple villages, typed on 5x7 note cards, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
    - Field notes on caste system in Gujarat, collected in multiple villages, typed on 5x7 note cards, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Notes, interview transcript, list of contacts for Bucknow-Bombay trip, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Notes on Kolis in India, census data, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Notes on Koli social roles, related correspondence, charts, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 4-8)
    - Notes on Gitel P. Steed’s "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat: The Social Use of Space," 1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Typescript titled "A Note on the Koli Status in Dhanpur Mahal," undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Notes on caste and Kolis, undated (Box 11, Folder 11-13)
    - Notes on Koli ideological and intellectual roles, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Notes on caste system in Bakrana, separated into the following categories: Rules & History, Dress & Hair-style, Occupations, and Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries 4: General Field Research Materials
    - Census handbooks for Ahmedabad District, 1941, 1951, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
    - Notes on psychological tests administered to villagers, 1949-1950 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Notes on logistics of research in India (number of researchers, hours needed, topics covered, etc.), 1950 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Inventories of clothing and equipment taken to India, itemized expense account, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Abstracts from Silverberg’s field diary, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Field notebooks, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 9-11)
    - Research notes on India, charts, graphs, drawings, 1950-1951 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Drawings, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Notes, both handwritten and typed, and bibliography on Gujarat, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Census data for different areas of India, Silverberg’s notes on this data, 1951, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Field notebooks, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Slide list (no slides included) titled "156-326: Peoples and Cultures of South Asia," 1952, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Transcripts and cassettes of interviews, 1970, This item has been reformatted for access. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of India, sent from Gitel Steed to Silverberg, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
    - India: Research materials related to study of energy resources, in particular the use of solar energy: Interview notes, correspondence, photograph, reports, notes, articles, 1976-79 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Land utilization survey conducted in Adon, India, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Notes on the conclusions of Silverberg's dissertation research, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Notes on farmer conflict in Durban, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Bibliography for dissertation research, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Photocopy of unidentified field notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Notes on the Gujarati language, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Notes on the Jajmani system, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified kinship chart, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Handwritten notes housed in folder titled "Historical Records (Khata Vati etc) for Village Study," undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Maps of peninsular Gujarat, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Road map of Delhi Province, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 5: General Files
    - One copy of Survey of India: Map Catalogue, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Collection of academic articles on various aspects of Indian culture and politics, notes, 1946-1957 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clipping from The Times of India, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - India map book, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper clippings of articles on India, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Materials regarding Camilo Torres, a Columbian Catholic priest turned guerrilla: Correspondence (including correspondence with Torres), newspaper clippings, one copy of The Catholic Worker (periodical), 1965-1973 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
    - Map of the Valley of Puebla, Mexico, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - One copy of Bibliography of World Applied Solar Energy Research (1940-1975), 1976 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - One copy of Guide to the Albert Mayer Papers on India, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Collection of published writings related to agriculture in India, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Notes on drug use in India, essays on drug use in India, floppy disks, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Notes on South Asian kinship, charts, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Notes on E.O. Moe’s Indian Agriculture: Present Condition - Prospective Changes, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Copies of chart detailing the Hindu religious calendar (based on M.M. Underhill’s The Hindu Religious Year), notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
    - Bibliography on India, undated (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
    - Photocopied foreign-language (Gujarati? Hindi?) typescript, undated (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Unidentified notes titled "Borradaile," undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Series IV: General Files
  This series contains a miscellany of materials. The first subseries is devoted to
  writings written by authors other than Silverberg. Subseries II contains materials
  related to Gitel P. Steed. While materials pertaining to Steed can be found
  throughout the James Silverberg Papers, the bulk of these materials have been
  housed here. Subseries III includes materials that do not fit within the established
  taxonomy of the collection: miscellaneous photographs, unidentified writings and
  notes, and press items. Of interest in this subseries are the diaries of Silverberg's
  wife, Donna. These diaries were written while Mrs. Silverberg was in India,
  accompanying her husband on the India Field Research Project. Lastly,
  Subseries IV contains several pottery items whose use and provenance are
  undetermined.
  - Subseries 1: Others’ Writings
    - Folklore Notes: Vol. I - Gujarat, 1914 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Review of Werner Levi’s Free India in Asia: Clipping, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Reprint copy of Margaret Mead’s "Manus Restudied: An Interim Report," 1954 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Village India: Studies in the Little Community ed. McKim Marriott, 1955 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Lore (publication of the Milwaukee Public Museum), 1958 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Papers from a symposium titled "Caste in India," abstracts, list of participants, correspondence, notes, name tag, 1958-1959 (Box 17, Folder 9-10)
    - Human Organization (journal), 1963 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Copies of Gerald D. Berreman articles published by the South Asia Series of the Center for South Asian Studies, University of California - Berkeley, 1966-1972 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Copy of A.M. Shah’s "Historical Sociology: A Trend Report," 1974 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Copies of publications put out by the Appropriate Technology Development Association (India), 1978 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Review of William L. Kolb’s "The Structure and Functions of Cities": Reprint, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Reprints and photocopied papers, published and unpublished, 1959-1984 (Box 18, Folder 6-8)
    - Reprints and photocopied papers, published and unpublished, 1959-1984 (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
    - Reprints and photocopied papers, published and unpublished, 1959-1984 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
    - Reprints and photocopied papers, published and unpublished, 1959-1984 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries 2: Materials Related to Gitel P. Steed
    - Newspaper clipping of story on Gitel Steed, 1949 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Typescript copy of report prepared by Gitel P. Steed in relation to the Research in Contemporary India Field Project, 1950 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Gitel P. Steed’s data index as sent to Dr. Kardiner, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Transcripts of lectures delivered by Gitel P. Steed at Columbia University as part of "Sociology 311-312: Techniques of Psychodynamic Analysis of Culture: Illustrated by Aspects of Primitive and Contemporary Societies," 1953 (Box 21, Folder 6-7)
    - of India Archive (Steed Papers), as compiled by Silverberg, 1979-1980, SEE ALSO Series II: Correspondence (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Materials related to Silverberg’s bequest to the Gitel P. Steed Papers at The University of Chicago Special Collections: Request to view Gitel P. Steed Papers at The University of Chicago Special Collections, notes, correspondence, 1994, SEE ALSO Series II: Correspondence (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Materials regarding the India archives at the Regenstein Library’s Special Collections: Notes, inventories, 1994, SEE ALSO Series II: Correspondence (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries 3: General Files
    - Notes on the organization of Silverberg’s research files, 1950 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper clipping of cartoon, 1950 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Donna Silverberg, diaries, 1950-1951 (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
    - Copies of feature story on Silverberg’s dissertation research, published by the University of Wisconsin - Madison, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper clipping of story on Silverberg, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Xth International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences: Correspondence, notes, copy of Silverberg’s "Intercultural Communication among Anthropologists: Tower of Babel or Siblinghood of Humanity?" 1978 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Typescript titled "Notes from Public Opinion Quarterly, winter 1952-53," undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified photos, undated (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified photocopied excerpt, undated (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries 4: Pottery
    - Brown shell/pod with a carved surface, undated (Box 24)
    - Ceramic bell, painted in blue and green, undated (Box 24)
    - Hollow coconut, filled with pottery fragments, undated (Box 24)
    - Small ceramic bowl with painted exterior, undated (Box 24)
    - Two smaller ochre ceramic goblet-shaped items with decorated surface and ashen interior, undated (Box 24)
    - Wine skin (Box 24)
    - Brown ceramic goblet-shaped item with ashen interior, undated (Box 25)
  - Series V: Oversize
    - Notes on Koli vocabulary regarding kinship, diagrams, photographs, undated (Box 26)
    - Hand drawn map of India, undated (Box 26)
  - Series VI: Restricted
    - Materials related to research funding, [Restricted 50 years: financial records] 1978-1989, 12 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)